Guide to the Kojima family papers M2117
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Kojima family papers
c. 1931-1960
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Kojima, Minoru
Kojima, Ishi
M2117
4 Linear Feet (2 boxes, 2 flat boxes)
Content Description
The materials include loose photographs, a photograph album, letters, ephemera such as Toshiko's school records, a "Memorial Chimes" boxed funeral album regarding Kenji Kojima, and other materials relating to the Kojima family and their struggle to re-establish their lives after World War II. Including over 120 letters, circa 1948-1960, most with their original mailing envelopes sent to Toshiko Kojima in New York City from her brother Minoru in Pasadena and other locations in California as well as when he was in the military, and letters from her mother Ichi Kojima in Pasadena.
Biographical / Historical
Kenji Kojima (1886-1947) and Ichi Kojima (born 1894) initially arrived in the United States in 1912 and settled in San Diego. Toshiko Kojima, their daughter, was born in San Diego in 1919, and her brother Minoru was born a few years later in 1923. Toshiko graduated from San Diego State College and went on to be an artist known for wood engraving. Minoru took up dentistry, establishing a practice in National City, CA, and eventually became part of the U.S. armed forces as a dentist. During World War II, the Kojima family was sent to an internment camp in Poston, Arizona, to which they occasionally allude in their letters.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was purchased for Stanford University, Special Collections in March 2014.
Japanese Americans -- California -- History -- 20th century; Kojima, Minoru; Kojima, Ishi; Kojima, Toshiko, 1919-
- Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 07/1948 to 10/1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 11/1948 to 12/1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 01/1949 to 05/1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 09/1949 to 11/1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 02/1950 to 06/1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 08/1950 to 12/1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 01/1951 to 02/1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 04/1951 to 10/1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 11/1951 to 12/1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 01/1952 to 06/1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 07/1952 to 10/1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 11/1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 03/1954 to 05/1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 07/1954 to 08/1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Awards and Certificates (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Kojima, Toshiko San Diego State College Transcripts (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Photographs (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
- San Diego State College Degree (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Palenque Fall, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- [Miscellaneous Book] (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Family Snapshot negatives (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Family Snapshot negatives (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Family Snapshot negatives (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Loose Pictures from Family Photograph Album (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Family Photograph Album circa 1940 (Flat-box 3)
  General
  Photographs are not adhered and can easily fall out so careful handling is required to keep integrity of album.
- "Memorial Chimes" boxed funeral album and papers (Flat-box 4)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains material regarding the death and service items, billing, arrangements, visitors book and condolences pertaining to Kenji Kojima (1886 - 1947), husband of Ishi K and father of Roshiko and Minoru. Includes memorial stone biling (with design) from Thos. Holmes and Sons Pasadena, items from Mountain View Cemetery and Crematorium in Pasadena CA, Los Angeles Co. hospital bills, receipts, sympathy cards, a small spiral notebook with date of 1947 at the hospital written entirely in columned Japanese, noting one name in English - the wake arrangements were held at the Edwards and Cummings funeral directors location in Pasadena. Adapted from seller's information.
- Two copper etching plates, "Construction Greek Theatre" and "Adobe Falls", approx. 5" x 7 1/2", probably made by Toshiko Kojima while at San Diego art school (Flat-box 4)